我⒎毙钦下
We pulled the stars from the skies...
用硌bc地球
...and brought them down to Earth.
代r是什N呢
But at what cost?
我c亮所有的敉r
When we turned on all these lights...
也失去了一些F的|西
we lost something precious.
繁星
The stars.
宇宙大探索
第八集
很久以前 只靠火光照亮
A long time ago, in a world lit only by fire,
我和繁星之g的PS
our relationship with the stars
非常的
was far more...
N心
personal.
浊Т人以
For thousands of generations,
我⒎毙且作生活不可或缺的部分
we watched the stars as if our lives depended on it.
_如此
Because they did.
我人不算最大
We humans were not the biggest, the strongest,
也不是最鸦蛘咦羁斓南啾绕渌游锒言
nor the fastest of all the animals we competed against.
但我有特L
But we did have one thing going for us...
我的智慧
our intelligence.
其中一c就是ReD形的天x
One aspect of that was a genius for pattern recognition
夜}一夜 我仰望星空
Night after night, we watched the stars.
我的祖先慢慢地注意到
And over time, our ancestors noticed
夜空中星星的移宇A示著地球上的化
that the motions of the stars across the nights of the year foretold changes on Earth
威that threatened or enhanced our chances for survival.
在我只能依靠想像力眢w故事的年代
In a time when our imaginations were the only stage where stories came to life,
那r]有影或者
before there were movies or TVs
也]有其他的子O
or electronic devices of any kind,
不同的文明⑦@些cB成各自不同的D案
every human culture connected the dots to form their own pictures.
@些D案成故事中的插D
These images became the illustrations of a storybook
更深用嬲f 也是一本生存手
that, on a deeper level, was also a survival manual.
天神和英雄的名字性
The names and personalities of the gods, heroes,
有游锘蛘哳似物w的名字和性
farm animals or familiar objects
在各文化中各不相同
varied from culture to culture.
除了一M特定的美星F
But there was one particularly gorgeous group of stars
墓畔ＥD人到F在的我都叫它
known to the Ancient Greeks and to us today
昴宿星F
as the Pleiades,
其位於金牛座 裸眼就可以p易的看 肉眼通常到有六w亮星
大s1|年前形成的星F
a star cluster formed about 100 million years ago.
每w星都比太明亮40倍左右
Each of them is some 40 times brighter than our Sun.
昴宿六是最亮的一w
And Alcyone, the most luminous,
比太亮1000倍
outshines our Sun 1,000 times.
以前昂宿星F被用zy力
For ages, the Pleiades have been used as an eye test
而且世界通用
for people all over the world.
能看到6w
If you could see at least six of them,
就是普通人的
you were considered normal.
看到超^7w
If you saw more than seven,
就符合鹗炕蛘刹毂的柿
you were an ideal candidate for a warrior or scout.
於古P特人和不列群u的德伊特碚f
Among the Ancient Celts and Druids of the British Isles,
他相信昂宿星F和亡魂有P
the Pleiades were believed to have a haunting significance.
一年中它升到天空最高c的那一晚的午夜
On the night of the year that they reach the highest point in the sky at midnight,
亡魂在地球上[
the spirits of the dead were thought to wander the Earth.
信@是一日的起源
This is believed to be the origin of the holiday
以前叫_毓
once known as Samhain,
F在叫f}
now called Halloween.
在世界各地 我的祖先用
All over the Earth, our ancestors told
各N神奇的故事
wonderful stories to explain
斫忉昂宿星F的v
how the Pleiades came to be in the sky.
以北美洲的基W瓦人碚f
For the Kiowa people of North America,
故事是@拥
it happened something like this.
很久很久以前 一些小姑娘
Long, long ago, some young women
溜出他的I地
snuck away from their campsite
在星空下o拘o束的跳舞
to dance freely beneath the stars.
山神 救命啊
Rock, save us!
山神 可z可z我吧
Rock, take pity on us!
山神到了她的哭 升起了一座高高的山峰
The rock heard their cries and grew taller.
成了今天的魔鬼峰
Until it became what is today known as the Devil's Tower.
@些姑娘成了昂宿星F的星星
The maidens were transformed into the stars of the Pleiades,
冬至的r候可以看到她高高的煸谏椒迳
which may be seen hanging above the tower in midwinter.
古希D人也⑦@7w明珠
The Ancient Greeks also saw those seven jewels
看做7位少女
as seven maidens,
阿特拉斯的7女
the seven daughters of Atlas,
以肩天的神
指的是C糇的那C
不是被熊追 而是被俄Y翁追
pursued not by bears, but by...Orion the hunter
他出砹镞_的r候看到了她
who spied them when he was out walking one day.
俄Y翁@C臬F性大l
Orion became mad with desire.
追了她7年 直到有一天
For seven years, he chased them relentlessly.
K於精疲力M了 -宙斯 救命啊
- Exhausted... - Zeus, help us.
她向宙斯呼救
...they prayed to Zeus for deliverance.
神之王宙斯大l慈悲
Zeus, the king of the gods, felt sorry for them,
把她7
and transformed those seven maidens
成了昂宿星F
into the Pleiades.
但是 神就是神病
But the gods are, if anything, capricious.
俄Y翁被子U死後
When Orion was killed by the sting of a scorpion,
宙斯把他放在上天 他可以^m追逐@7位姐妹
Zeus placed him in the sky where he could resume his pursuit of the seven gorgeous sisters
我的祖先了各N美的髡f
Our ancestors, they wove brilliantly imaginative stories
但是除了想像 K不能我更接近@些星星
But they can bring us no closer to the stars than our dreams
直到很多年後
It took yet another few thousand years
才有3位明的科W家揭_了@些星星的神秘面
until three brilliant scientists unlocked the secrets of the true lives of the stars
1901年
In 1901,
哈佛是男人的天下
Harvard was a man's world.
直到一位名叫鄣氯A・查理斯・皮克林的天文W家
But an astronomer named Edward Charles Pickering
打破了@矩
broke that rule.
噢 皮克林的k公室就在走廊M^
Oh, Pickering's office is just down the hallway.
那扇T的後面
And that door over there leads to the room
就是他的C房
where he keeps his computers.
f起 @些女人都是「算器」 但是
We're supposed to call those women "computers," but, uh,
我到不少人叫她
I've heard more than one fellow refer to those gals
皮克林的後m
as "Pickering's Harem."
皮克林招募了一群D女
Pickering assembled a team of women
o星星分 Lu星D
to map and classify the types of stars.
其中一位槲t解恒星的物|提供了
One of them provided the key to our understanding
PI的匙
of the substance of the stars.
有一位o我提供了算
And another devised a way for us to calculate
宇宙we的方法
the size of the universe.
你可能]f^她
For some reason, you probably never heard of either of them.
想知道原因
Wonder why.
@小M的ML名叫安妮・坎r
That's Annie Jump Cannon, the leader of the team.
完成r
Before she was through,
她分了25fw恒星
she catalogued a quarter of a million stars.
11是一wB7星
Number 11 is a B7.
那是昂宿星F的昂宿六
That's Alcyone in the Pleiades.
在坎r年p的r候
Cannon lost her hearing during a bout of scarlet fever
她不幸因楦腥拘杉t岫适Я寺力
when she was a young woman.
12是一wB6星
Number 12 is a B6.
那是亨鬯・勒S特 也是失
That's Henrietta Swan Leavitt. She's also deaf.
她是@Y的另一位ゴ蟮目W家
And she's the other great scientist in the room.
勒S特l明了天文W家沿用上百年的方法
Leavitt discovered the law that astronomers still use more than a century later
用y量恒星之g的距x
to measure the distances to the stars
有宇宙的we
and the size of the cosmos itself.
安妮・坎r在一R卡中f明了
Annie Jump Cannon sent out a Christmas card explaining
她正在氖碌墓ぷ
what she and her sisters were actually doing.
恒星l出的光可以
The light from a star is allowed
通^望hR中的棱R 她道
to fall through a prism placed in the telescope, she wrote.
^放大 星光可以分解成一M色
Thus magnified, the starlight is split up into a band
@示出M成的色
showing its component colors,
t光和紫光分e於啥
the red rays going to one end and the violet to the other.
@就是恒星的光V
This is the spectrum of the star.
由深色表示
It shows the presence of fine, dark lines.
⑦@些c室中l光物|做Ρ
By comparing them with lines given by glowing substances in the laboratory
我可以喽ㄟ@些地球上熟悉的物|
we can determine that the same elements familiar to us
同哟嬖陟哆bh的恒星上
on the Earth also exist in the outermost star.
@是12358B
This is plate number 12358B.
@K板上的第一是wB星
Number one at this plate is a B-type star.
定B2
Make that a B2.
坎r用了资年
It took Cannon decades
按照光V特性
to classify the spectral character
槌汕上f的恒星分Te
of hundreds of thousands of stars
根她制定的方法
according to the scheme that she devised.
坎rJ楹阈强梢
Cannon discovered that the stars fell
根它的光VD被分7大
into a continuous sequence of seven broad categories according to their spectral line patterns.
每大由一字母代表
Each was designated by a letter.
但是相同e的深w恒星的光V
But the spectral lines of two stars in the same letter class
可能有著微的^e
could differ in subtle ways,
坎r根察X到的微化
minute variations that Cannon learned to recognize from memory.
榱^分@些光V
To distinguish these spectra from one another,
她又⒚看箢分10用底执表的小
she assigned ten numerical subcategories for each class.
安妮・坎r⒑阈w
Annie Jump Cannon organized the stars,
另一位科W家解密她的成果中[藏的含x
but it would fall to another scientist to decipher the hidden meaning in her work
1923年的英格m D女o
In the England of 1923, women were forbidden
在科W上@得高W位
from pursuing advanced degrees in science.
但是塞西莉・佩恩在敦⒓恿艘v座
But Cecelia Payne had attended a lecture in London
由瑟・鄱☆D爵士演v
by the astronomer Sir Arthur Eddington,
他是首位C
the first scientist to provide evidence
垡蛩固Vx相φ的科W家
that Einstein's revolutionary General Theory of Relativity was correct.
哪r起
From that moment on,
她知道]什N可以阻跛
she knew that nothing would deter her
追求她的粝
from pursing her big dreams.
她Q定移居美
She resolved to emigrate to America,
在那YD女已有了研究恒星的自由
where women had already gained the freedom to study the stars.
哈佛大W接受了她的申
Her application was accepted at Harvard.
她S後的lF改了一天文W的基本^c
What she would discover there would challenge one of the central beliefs of astronomy.
造成的影就如同F代天文物理W的曙光
The resulting impact would be the dawn of modern astrophysics.
资年^去了
As the decades passed,
安妮・坎r和她的MT不嗟睾Y分恒星
Annie Jump Cannon and her team kept sifting the stars,
z查每一w的光V特徵
checking each one's spectral signature
K⑺w入
with a fleeting glance and then dropping them
7大分中
into one of seven categories.
它成了D片中成千上f的D元
They became hundreds of thousands of dots
在r]人能虿t解它的含x
in a larger picture which no one could yet understand.
@支伍中又砹艘晃恍碌某T
Into this community of women came one more.
哈D
Well, hello there.
你就是佩恩吧
You must be Miss Payne.
等你好久啦
We've been waiting for you.
快M
Come on in.
塞西莉・佩恩第一次在科研h境中受到@拥g迎
Cecilia Payne had never experienced such kindness in a scientific setting before.
姐妹o私的c她分享研究成果
This sisterhood generously shared the fruits of their labors with her,
她⑺的^察Y果
and she turned their observations
D化成一N恒星的全新JR
into a radical new understanding of the stars.
女人成了非常要好的朋友
The two women became great friends.
坎r把恒星光Vε宥A囊相授
Cannon taught Payne everything she had learned about stellar spectra
佩恩著手分析坎r的Y料
And Payne began to analyze Cannon's data
L著判嗪阈侵械幕W成分c物理B
to see if she could determine the actual chemical composition and physical state of the stars
她l]了她的理原子物理WｉL
She brought to this work her expertise in theoretical and atomic physics
恒星光V中最突出的特徵
The most prominent features in the spectra of stars
@示了重金僭素的存在 比如} 和F
showed the presence of heavy elements such as calcium... and iron,
地球上最常的那些元素
which are among the most abundant elements in the Earth.
天文W家自然而然的得出Y
So astronomers naturally concluded
恒星是由c地球相同的物|M成
that the stars were made of the same elements as the Earth
就B比例都大致相同
and in roughly the same proportions.
1924年 r的美天文W泰斗亨利・Z利斯・_素
In 1924, Henry Norris Russell was the dean
槲於恒星的t解做出了重大的I
of American astronomers having made major contributions to our understanding of the stars.
地球上的40到45化W元素
40 to 45 of the chemical elements that we have here on Earth
一哟嬖谂c太的光V中
are also present in the spectrum of the Sun.
所以我可以推嗵的成分
So we can assume that the composition of the Sun
c地球似
resembles that of the Earth.
如果有人能把地ぜ岬桨l出光芒
If one were to heat the crust of the Earth to incandescence,
它的光V就和太似
its spectrum would resemble that of the Sun.
安妮 我明白了@N多年砟愕墓ぷ鞒晒的真正意x
Annie, I think I now understand what it all means. All your years of work.
f砺
Tell me.
我算了不同囟认碌墓庾V
I've calculated what the spectra should look like across a wide range of temperatures,
它和你的分法完美吻合
and they match your system of classification perfectly
恒星的光V可以表示它的囟
The spectrum of any star tells you exactly how hot it is.
你的OBAFGKM就是恒星的
Your "O-B-A-F-G-K-M" is really a temperature scale of the stars
OBAFGKM=哈佛分法 各字母代表不同的光Ve
淖岬阶罾
from the hottest to the coldest.
重c砹 安妮 多了你
Here's the headline, Annie. Thanks to your work,
我lF 恒星缀跞部是由浜秃そM成
I've discovered that the stars are made almost entirely of hydrogen and helium.
恒星中的浜秃け冉俣嗌习偃f倍
There's a million times more hydrogen and helium than the metals in the stars
我知道上去好像挺傻
I know, it sounds daft.
你_定
Are you certain?
有人核^你的算Y果
Has anyone else checked your calculations?
] 我都M我的文Y了
Not yet, but it's all in my thesis,
已寄o_素教授了
which is already on its way to Professor Russell.
倒楣孩子
Poor woman.
_素λ表示z憾
Russell felt sorry for Cecilia Payne.
在他看 她的文母本上就是e的
Her thesis appeared to him to be fundamentally flawed.
@然浜秃げ豢赡鼙冉俣嗌习偃f倍
It is clearly impossible that hydrogen should be a million times more abundant than the metals.
她仔收集的Cc鹘y的科W^c不相符
Her carefully gathered evidence flew in the face of conventional scientific wisdom.
我怎N可能是Φ 她
"How could I be right," she asked,
那就意味著
"if that must mean
那N著名的科W家e了
that such a distinguished scientist was wrong?"
管她ψ约旱难芯拷Y果很自信
Despite her confidence in the quality of her research,
她是在她的文里加上了一句 「高的缀蹩梢钥隙ú徽」
she caved and added a sentence to her thesis
u了@非常ゴ蟮挠^c
that undermined its greatest insight.
4年後
It would be four years
_素才意R到佩恩是正_的
before Russell realized that Payne was right.
值得表P的是 他一JR到@c
To his credit, as soon as he did,
他就承J了 @是佩恩的lF
he acknowledged that it was her discovery.
佩恩的《恒星大狻繁黄毡榭醋鍪
Payne's "Stellar Atmospheres" is widely regarded
天文W有史以碜艹龅牟┦空文
as the most brilliant PhD thesis ever written in astronomy.
它成了@I域Y教科
It became the standard text in its field.
]有猿治业挠^c是我的任
I was to blame for not having pressed my point.
管我相信自己的正_ s是屈服于嗤
I had given in to authority when I believed I was right.
如果你ψ约旱慕Y有把握
If you are sure of your facts,
你就猿帜愕牧
you should defend your position.
恒星大W
在其他I域 嗤的言可能
The words of the powerful may prevail in other spheres of human experience
但科W碚f 最PI的是C
but in science, the only thing that counts is the evidence
以及h本身的性
and the logic of the argument itself.
佩恩解了安妮坎r的恒星光V序列
Cecilia Payne's interpretation of Annie Jump Cannon's sequence
使我可以理解恒星生命的故事
of stellar spectra made it possible for us to read the life stories of the stars
K且根@乃燃的Kc追溯回它的起源
and to trace the story of life itself back to its beginnings in their fiery deaths.
有很多N恒星
There are many kinds of stars.
一些像太般明亮
Some are bright like the Sun.
有些暗淡
Some are dim.
最大的恒星比最小的要大上千f倍
The greatest stars are ten million
times larger than the smallest ones
有些恒星古老的超出想像
Some stars are old beyond imagining,
超^100|q
more than ten billion years of age.
有些才Q生
Others are being born right now.
原子在恒星的核心中融合
When atoms fuse in the hearts of stars,
它l出星光
they make starlight.
恒星碾s物中Q生
Stars are born in litters,
由星H的怏w和灰mM成
formed from the gas and dust of interstellar clouds.
不同恒星的品|差
The mass of the individual stars in a litter
男〉哪切 K不比最大的行星大多少
can range from the runts--not much larger than the largest planets--
到大的那些超巨星 太都相形I
to the supergiant stars that dwarf the Sun.
C糇腰下方星中的恒星Q生
The stars in the nebula below Orion's Belt are newborns,
差不多500fq
around five million years old,
被包裹在Q生r的怏w和灰m中
and still swaddled in the gas and dust that gave birth to them.
昂宿星F中的恒星已到了跚W步的年o
The stars in the Pleiades are already toddlers,
1|q左右
about 100 million years old.
它已甩_了怏w和灰m的遮w
They've shed their blankets of gas and dust,
但依然被彼此的引力束`在一起
but they're still bound together by their mutual gravity.
再^|年
Another few hundred million years,
它才各奔|西
and they'll drift apart and go their separate ways,
拇嗽俨幌嘁
never to meet again.
北斗星中的大部分恒星已是青少年了
Most of the stars of the Big Dipper are adolescents,
5|q左右
roughly half a billion years old.
它已x_了出生r的星F
They've already drifted apart from their birth cluster,
不^ 我是能找到它共同的祖先
although we can still trace their common ancestry.
最K 它散落在y河系中
Eventually, they'll spread out around the Milky Way galaxy.
但是大部分常的星座
But most of the familiar constellations
是由完全不相P的恒星混合而成
are a mix of entirely unrelated stars,
有些暗淡而相距不h
some faint and nearby,
有些明亮hh相隔
others bright and far away.
我的太呢
Our own Sun?
坠饽觊_外看去 也很y找到其他相近的恒星
From the distance of even a few light-years, it's hard to find amidst the other stars.
那
It's that one.
我的太已M中年
Our Sun is middle-aged
x_出生地也很h了
and a long way from where it was born.
耐一星HQ生的姐妹星
Its sister stars hatched from the same interstellar cloud,
分散在y河系各
are dispersed throughout the galaxy.
S多都有它各自的行星
Many of them have their own planets.
或S有些已孕育了
Perhaps some of them nurture
智慧生物和生命的M化
the evolution of life and intelligence.
夜空中的大多岛阈
Most of the stars in our night sky
h@一或多恒星小夥伴\行
actually orbit around one or more stellar companions.
在@Np星或者多星的系y 靠我的肉眼
With the naked eye, we usually can't see the fainter members
通常看不到^暗的那些星
in such double and multiple star systems.
在有3太的世界Y
On a world with three suns,
很少有夜晚
the nights would be rare
白天也在t色和and the days might alternate between red and blue.
恒星的坍s是]定的
It is the destiny of stars to collapse.
抬^看向夜空 所看到的成千上f的星星
Of the thousands of stars you see when you look up at the night sky,
每一都活在纱翁s之g
every one of them is living in an interval between two collapses...
黑暗的星H怏wF的第一次坍s
an initial collapse of a dark, interstellar gas cloud
形成了恒星
to form the star,
明亮恒星的最後一次坍s
and a final collapse of the luminous star
是它的生命M^
on its way to its ultimate fate.
]有外力干_的情r下 引力使恒星收s
Gravity makes stars contract, unless some other force intervenes
太是怏wM成的大球w
The Sun is a great, big ball of incandescent gas.
核心的超高怏w
The super hot gas in its core
促使太向外U
pushes the Sun to expand outward.
c此同r 太的引力
At the same time,the Sun's own gravity
又使它向仁湛s
pulls it inward to contract.
我的太在煞N力定平衡的B
And our Sun is poised between these two forces in a stable equilibrium
引力和核爆炸
between gravity and nuclear fire,
@N平衡^m
a balance it will maintain
保持40|年
for another four billion years.
太消耗
But as the Sun consumes hydrogen,
它的核心慢慢的收s
its core very slowly shrinks,
而它的表面s在逐步的U
and the Sun's surface gradually expands in response.
在装偃f年的rgY ^程很慢 不易察X
It happens very slowly,imperceptibly, over the course of millions of years
但於10|年碚f
But in about a billion years,
太比F在亮出百分之10
the Sun will be ten percent brighter than it is today
百分之10 上去不多
Ten percent may not sound like much,
但@些~外的崃Φ厍蛟斐珊艽蟮挠绊
but that extra heat will have a big effect on Earth.
太最K耗M它的核燃料
When the Sun finally exhausts its nuclear fuel
40或者50|年後
four or five billion years from now,
怏w冷s 毫下降
its gas will cool and the pressure will fall.
太的炔o法^m支瓮拥闹亓
The Sun's interior can no longer support the weight of the outer layers
最初的坍s再次^m
and the initial collapse will resume.
f物都]有永a
Nothing lasts forever.
恒星也死
Even the stars die.
氦 100|年渚圩的灰a
Helium, the ash of ten billion years of hydrogen fusion,
在核心中【
has built up in the core.
]有核爆炸支持它的重量
With no nuclear fire to sustain its weight,
群颂s 囟雀叩拈_始⒑ぞ酆铣商己脱
the core collapses until it becomes hot enough to start fusing helium into carbon and oxygen
太群说囟缺纫郧案吆芏
The core of the Sun is now much hotter than it was before.
它的大饧∨蛎
Its atmosphere rapidly expands.
在接下淼10|年Y 它膨到
Over the next billion years, it'll become bloated
超^F在we的100倍
to more than 100 times its original size
成一wt巨星
a red giant star.
它覆wK吞噬
It will envelop and devour
水星
the planets Mercury...
金星
...and Venus...
很可能有地球
...and possibly the Earth.
我J
I like to think that
在那之前的浊f年
tens of millions of years before that far distant future,
如果地球上有生命Q生
if there still be life born of Earth,
它已在其他星球找到了新家
it will have found new homes among the stars.
一旦太燃M所有的氦
Once the Sun burns through its helium,
它就_始得非常不定
it will become highly unstable,
⑺的L甩向太空
casting off its outer layers into space.
超炙岬穆懵逗诵
The exposed, super hot core
l出高能量的紫外 潮水般淹]四周
will flood its surroundings with high-energy ultraviolet light.
原子l著光 狂的×一
The atoms will perform a wild, fluorescent dance.
太像蛋奶酥一拥氖湛s塌陷
The Sun will collapse like a souffle
s小到地球we的装俦
shrinking a hundredfold to the size of the Earth.
到那r 太O度o密 ^度D的子_始相互排D
And at that point, the Sun will be so dense that its overcrowded electrons will push back,
一切收s都停止了
stopping any further contraction.
只有太中心的光核依然猿衷谀茄Y
The kernel of light at the center will be the only part of the Sun that endures
成了白矮星 它^ml出微弱的光
a white dwarf star that will go on shining dimly
再持m1千|年
for another 100 billion years.
bh未淼纳命
Will the beings of a distant future,
倪@w星的骸旁路^
sailing past this wreck of a star,
想到它曾照耀^得那些生命和世界
have any idea of the life and worlds that it once warmed?
普通恒星死亡r的炫目光罩D瞬即逝
The psychedelic death shrouds of ordinary stars are fleeting,
只延m兹f年的rg
lasting only tens of thousands of years
然後消散成星H怏w和灰m
before dissipating in the interstellar gas and dust
新的恒星又闹姓Q生
from which the new stars will be born.
星系y中的恒星
The stars in a binary star system
可以有不一拥拿\
can have a different fate.
天狼星 夜空中最亮那w星
Sirius, the brightest star in the night sky,
有一非常暗淡的伴S者
has a very faint stellar companion--
一w白矮星
a white dwarf.
曾像太一
It was once a Sun-like star.
有一天 天狼星耗M了燃料
Someday, when Sirius runs out of fuel
成了t巨星
and becomes a red giant,
它的物|流向白矮星
it will shed its substance onto the white dwarf.
@位伴S者的大引力吸引怏w
The intense gravity of the companion will attract that gas,
使它形成一螺旋畹AP
pulling it into a spiraling disk.
妮^大恒星出淼怏w
When the gas from the larger star
落在白矮星的表面
falls onto the surface of the white dwarf,
引l核爆炸
it will trigger nuclear explosions.
最大模的爆炸放
The greatest burst will release
超^太10f倍的能量
100,000 times more energy than the Sun.
每一次的爆炸被Q 新星
Each one of those star bursts is called a "nova,"
Nova：新星
在拉丁Z中就是 新 的意思
from the Latin for "new."
一w品|相於15太的恒星
A star about 15 times as massive as the Sun,
比如⑺奁 一wone like Rigel, the blue supergiant
C糇的右_
that forms the right foot of Orion,
就有著不同的命\
has a different fate in store.
子的毫Σ使它的坍s停止
Its collapse will not be stopped by the pressure of electrons.
它持m坍s
The star will keep falling in on itself,
直到原子核^度D
until its nuclei become so overcrowded
_始相互排斥
that they push back.
⑺奁s小差不多10f倍
Rigel will shrink down about 100,000 times,
直到原子核之g]有距x
until there's no space left between the nuclei
o法再s小
and it can shrink no more.
到那r 它引l
At that point, it ignites
一龈烈的核反 超新星
a more powerful nuclear reaction, a supernova.
大部分的恒星演
Most stellar evolution
要v装偃f或者资|年
takes millions or billions of years.
但是炔康奶s
But the interior collapse
引l超新星爆炸只需要酌腌
that triggers a supernova explosion takes only seconds.
只剩下一原子核
What remains will be an atomic nucleus
一小城市那N大
the size of a small city--
急速旋D的中子星被Q }n星
a rapidly rotating neutron star called a pulsar.
但於品|超^太30倍的恒星
But for a star more than 30 times as massive as the Sun--
比如⑺薅 在C糇的腰上
a star like Alnilam, in Orion's Belt--
]什N可以阻止它的坍s
there will be no stopping its collapse.
装偃f年後
In a few million years,
⑺薅燃殆M
when Alnilam runs out of fuel,
它也成超新星
it, too, will go supernova.
崩⒌⑺薅核心
The imploding core of Alnilam
品|大得 即使核力也不足以承受它的坍s
will be so massive that not even nuclear forces
will be strong enough to hold off its collapse.
]有什N可以抵抗@N引力
Nothing can withstand such gravity.
密度如此@人的恒星
And such a star has an astonishing destiny.
它持m坍s
It will continues to collapse,
超越r空的界限
crossing a boundary in space-time
Q 界
called the "event horizon,"
即黑洞表面
我o法看到炔
beyond which we cannot see.
它穿那界限
When it traverses that frontier,
星星奈的 消失得o影o
the star will vanish completely from sight.
它在黑洞
It will be inside a black hole,
那Y的引力o比大 即使光也o法逃
a place where gravity is so strong that nothing, not even light, can escape.
有一N罕的恒星有著更』的命\
But there's an even more dramatic fate that awaits a rare kind of star
我的y河系就有一w
There's one of them in our galaxy.
它很不定 它爆炸r
It's so unstable that when it goes,
它不成新星或者超新星
it won't become a mere nova or supernova.
它成更大的碾y
It'll become something far more catastrophic...
O超新星
a hypernova.
在我@子就可能l生
And it could happen in our lifetime.
澳洲汝是地球上最好的星空^y地c之一
There are few places on Earth to get a better view of the night sky than the Australian Outback.
]有建B物
No buildings,
] ]路 什N都]有
no cars, streetlights, nothing out here;
只有星光
just lots of starlight...
偶有纂b袋鼠
and the occasional kangaroo.
在@Y 你可以非常好的^察y河系
You can get a particularly good view of the Milky Way from down here.
y河的中心
The center of our galaxy
高以诳罩
rises high in the sky,
拱形穿^天空
and it arches across the heavens
就像黑夜的脊
like the backbone of night.
我的y河系是螺旋星
We live in a spiral galaxy.
我看向y河r
And when we look at the Milky Way,
我可以看到螺旋AP中资|w恒星l出的光
we're seeing light from billions of stars in its spiral disk.
在@用利的夜空下
And under this beautiful dark sky,
你能看到y河K不是一片明亮
you can see that the Milky Way isn't a uniform band of light.
有些黑色的斑K遮掩了星光
There are dark patches, breaks in the starlight.
那些黑色的斑K就是星Hm埃
Those dark patches are caused by interstellar dust.
盗勘多的m埃阻趿诵枪
The dust blocks the starlight, and there's lots of it.
大部分的文明中 ⑿切窍噙B
Most cultures looked up at the stars and connected the dots
在夜空中M成熟悉的D案
to form familiar images in the sky.
星座
Constellations.
但是澳洲土著
But the Aboriginal people of Australia
注意到了黑影的形
saw a pattern in the darkness
穿y河
running through the Milky Way.
看上去像 一N大B 一N澳洲大本土游
They saw an emu, a large bird native to this continent.
它K不是由星星M成 而是在]有星星的地方悄然出F
Not in the stars,but in the absence of stars.
有不用的方式砜葱强
There are so many ways to look at the night sky.
上百f年的rgY
For a million years or more, we've watched the sky.
l生了很多事
And a lot's happened in that time.
我的y河系中超新星爆炸大s100年一次
Supernova explode in our galaxy about once a century.
如果我把所有b望星空的夜晚嚎s成一分
If we could compress all those nights of stargazing into a single minute
@是我可以看到的景象
this is what we would see.
如果把我的眼睛比做望hR
Now, if our eyes were telescopes,
口胶蛙一哟
if they were light buckets as big as wagon wheels
我又可以Re不HH一N光r
and our vision was not limited to just one kind of light,
我看到的y河系就是@拥
then this is the Milky Way we would see.
近t外光中的星系
A galaxy in near-infrared light
|手般四蔓延的m埃
with streaming tendrils of dust
被爆炸的超新星猛烈地甩出
hurled outward by those exploding supernovas,
在o敌切堑挠骋r下@F出
silhouetted against a backdrop of countless stars
大s7500光年以外
About 7,500 light-years away,
y河系的另一端
in another part of our galaxy,
有一鼍拮
there is a place of upheaval
模大得y以想像
on an inconceivable scale.
@是船底座星
This is the Carina Nebula.
一台恒星u造C
A star-making machine.
光要用50年的rg才能穿
It takes a ray of light 50 years to cross it.
巨大的恒星在@YQ生
The titanic stars born here
烈的紫外射烤焦了周的怏w和m埃
sear the surrounding gas and dust with their fierce ultraviolet radiation.
巨大的恒星死亡r
When a massive star dies,
⑺自己炸成碎片
it blows itself to smithereens.
它的物|被推得四w
Its substance is propelled across the vastness
被星光
to be stirred by starlight
被引力【
and gathered up by gravity.
由恒星成m埃
Stars to dust
再由m埃楹阈
and dust to stars.
宇宙中 ]有U物
In the cosmos, nothing is wasted.
但是恒星的品|有一上限
But there's an upper limit to how massive a star can be.
17世or 鄣旅伞す雷
Back in the 17th century, when Edmond Halley
跨^赤道 Lu南方的星座D
crossed the equator to map the southern constellations,
海山二看上去只是一w暗星
Eta Carinae seemed like just another faint star.
一位於船底星座
但到了1843年 海山二
But in 1843, Eta Carinae
突然成了天空中第二亮的星
suddenly became the second brightest star in the sky,
只是比天狼星稍暗
outshined only by Sirius.
拇碎_始爆l
And it's been flipping out ever since.
那♀形的F
That dumbbell-shaped cloud
就是爆l的膨N
is the expanding remnant of that event.
中心是一w狂的恒星
At its center is one crazy star.
f到不定
Talk about unstable
海山二比太的品|大出至少100倍
Eta Carinae is at least 100 times more massive than the Sun,
K且l出比太多500f倍的光
and pouring out five million times more light.
它一直在挑鸷阈瞧焚|的上限
It's pushing the upper limit of what a star can be.
有 有C@示 海山二
What's more, there's evidence that Eta Carinae
受它那邪盒值艿闹亓φ勰
is being gravitationally tormented by an evil twin--
那是一w@它\行的恒星
another massive star in orbit around it
之g的距x就像土星到太的距x
as close as Saturn is to the Sun.
超巨大的恒星群税l出大量的光
The core of a supermassive star pours out so much light
以致向外的毫ιw^了恒星的引力
that the outward pressure can overwhelm the star's gravity.
如果恒星^於巨大
If a star is too massive,
它的射毫Τ^它的引力
its radiation pressure overpowers its gravity
就⑦@w星炸裂
and blows the star apart.
海山二的命\
The fate of Eta Carinae was sealed
在装偃f年前Q生r就已]定
when it was born millions of years ago.
它最K爆炸r
When it finally does blow up
f不定 已爆炸了
and who knows, maybe it already has;
竟 我看到的光
after all, we're looking at it by light that left the star
是7500年前l出的
7,500 years ago--
那是我]^的大碾y
it will be a cataclysm unlike anything we've seen before.
O超新星
A hypernova.
爆炸威力大得使超新星看上去就如同鞭炮一
An explosion so powerful, it'll make a supernova seem like a firecracker by comparison.
如果附近有太系
If there are nearby solar systems
伴S有生命的行星 它的死期到了
with planets harboring life, their days are numbered.
O超新星出大量的射
A hypernova spews so much radiation into space--
不只光 有X射 伽R射
not just light, but X-rays and gamma rays--
资光年外的行星
that planets that are dozens
或者甚至装俟饽晖獾
or perhaps hundreds of light-years away
都适它的大
could be stripped of their atmospheres
然後被死亡射\罩
and bathed in deadly radiation.
它可以肆虐周浊恒星系y
It would wreak havoc in thousands of nearby star systems.
F在 你可能好奇
Right about now, you're probably asking yourself,
我安全
"Are we safe?"
如果海山二爆炸
If Eta Carinae blows up,
地球怎Nk
what happens to Earth?
放心吧 地球不有事
Rest assured, Earth will be just fine.
住 我x它7500光年呢
Remember, we're 7,500 light-years away from Eta Carinae.
恒星放出的射度
The intensity of radiation from a star,
即使是一w爆炸的恒星
even an exploding star,
S著距x急∠陆
falls off rapidly with distance.
即使@ 海山二的x幕演出
But still, Eta Carinae in its death throes
依然非常精彩
will put on quite a show.
它c亮南半球的夜空
It will light up the night of the southern hemisphere
亮得如同月亮一
with the brightness of a second moon.
奉I上最激尤诵牡母e演出
The most dramatic swan song a star can sing.
我的祖先崇拜太
Our ancestors worshipped the Sun.
他^不是愚蠢
And they were far from foolish.
μ和恒星的崇拜很有道理
It makes good sense to revere the Sun and stars,
因槲是它的孩子
because we are their children.
岩石中的矽 空庵械难
The silicon in the rocks, the oxygen in the air,
DNA中的碳 摩天大侵械蔫F
the carbon in our DNA, the iron in our skyscrapers,
珠中的y
the silver in our jewelry
都是恒星资|年前造的
were all made in stars billions of years ago.
我的星球 我的社 有我自己
Our planet, our society and we ourselves
都是星m
are stardust.
是什N使原子@N活S
Well, what is it that makes the atoms dance?
恒星的能量是如何D
How is the energy of a star transformed
世界上所l生的一切呢
into everything that happens in the world?
什N是能量
What is energy?
我都身其中
We're awash in it.
湓子在太中聚合
When hydrogen atoms fuse inside the Sun,
a生氦原子
they make helium atoms.
@N核聚l出一股能量
And this fusion emits a burst of energy
可以在太炔窟[1千f年
that can wander inside the Sun for ten million years
然後到_表面
before making its way to the surface.
然後@得自由
And once there, it's free to fly
直接向地球w
straight from the Sun to the Earth
就是可光
as visible light.
如果它撞粼谌~子的表面
If it should strike the surface of a leaf,
它就被作榛W能量保存在了地球
it will be stored in the plant as chemical energy.
日光
Sunshine...
成月光
into moonshine.
@Y指的是一N威士卡
我能感受到我的大X把葡萄酒的化W能量
I can feel my brain turning the chemical energy of the wine
D樗枷氲碾能
into the electrical energy of my thoughts
指]我的
and directing my vocal chords
a生我f的能
to produce the acoustic energy of my voice.
@N能量的DQ
Such transformations of energy
oro刻都在l生
are happening everywhere all the time.
太的能量
Energy from our star
语L和浪
drives the wind and the waves
有我四周的生命
and the life around us.
有@哟罅康那能源是多N幸\的事情
How lucky we are to have this vast source of clean energy
@直是o所有人的天n之物
falling like manna from heaven on all of us.
敬 安妮・坎r
To Annie Jump Cannon,
亨鬯・勒S特
Henrietta Swan Leavitt
有塞西莉・佩恩
and Cecilia Payne
感x她_了F代天文物理W
for blazing the trail to modern astrophysics.
要敬 太的所有姐妹
And to all the sisters of the Sun.
宇宙中一切都逃不^改
There's no refuge from change in the cosmos.
默F在以後的壹千f或汕f年
Some ten or 20 million years from now,
在宇宙中只是片刻
it'll seem for a cosmic moment
彷佛C舳硌Y翁K於要抓到七姐妹了
as if Orion is finally about to catch the seven sisters.
但在他抓住她之前
But before he has them in his clutches,
C糇最大的最w恒星就成超新星
the biggest stars of Orion will go supernova.
C糇Π核扌亲的追s拇送Ｖ
Orion's pursuit of the Pleiades will finally end,
那七位姐妹
and the seven sisters
地投入y河系的臂
will glide serenely into the waiting arms of the Milky Way
我在地球上μ升起l出U
We on Earth marvel and rightly so-- at the return of our solitary Sun.
在bh的球钚请中 囊h@恒星的行星上看
But from a planet orbiting a star in a distant globular cluster,
能看到更多@W的黎明
a still more glorious dawn awaits.
不是太升起
Not a sunrise...
而是星系的升起
but a galaxy rise.
2千|w太照耀的早晨
A morning filled with 200 billion suns.
y河系的升起
The rising of the Milky Way.
巨大的螺旋畎殡S者坍塌的怏wF
An enormous spiral form with collapsing gas clouds,
凝Y的行星系y l光的超巨星
condensing planetary systems, luminous supergiants,
定的中年太，t巨星，白矮星
stable middle-aged suns, red giants, white dwarfs,
行星钚请 超新星
planetary nebulas, supernovas,
中子星 }n星 黑洞
neutron stars, pulsars, black holes
有充分的理由J
and, there is every reason to think,
有其他的天w 我尚未lF
other exotic objects that we have yet to discover.
倪@拥囊世界 高异躲y河系
From such a world, high above the Milky Way,
@N的清晰 清晰地如同我世界起源r
it would be clear, as it is beginning to be clear on our world,
我由原子和星M成
that we are made by the atoms and the stars,
我的物| 我的形B
that our matter and our form
由ゴ蠖古老的宇宙造
are forged by the great and ancient cosmos,
我也是@宇宙的一部分
of which we are a part.